For Bisky, how much would he help you
just having a veteran back up and how
much could he help Cam?
>> I I I think it's going to elevate, you
know,
uh whoever the backup is. I think it's
really going to elevate that room. So,
Will Will is coming off his shoulder uh
uh
injury and uh you know, I don't let's
not close the door on him either. You
know, Trubisky's had has had a
tremendous career and we're really
really excited to have him, but he's
really going to elevate the competition
in that room and uh really excited for
those two to uh
uh have unbelievable off seasons. How
have you grown as a head coach
and I think that and obviously it's
important to learn from everything you
have your convictions, but then you also
look for room to grow, too. What have
you tried to Where have you tried to
grow the most? Um you you grow through
experience like um you know, the
obviously I feel like I'm more prepared
now than I was the first time I took the
job and uh you know, things aren't as as
shocking when they happen, but um
but you're always going to evolve even
even today I'm I'm going to be I'm going
to know a hell of a lot more by the end
of the year than I did today. So, it's
it's constantly keeping an open book
uh keeping an open mind um and absorbing
as much information as you can, not
being stagnant in what you do, trying to
evolve every day and uh so it's a uh
it's an
it's a uh it's it's always evolving.
That's what that was. As you kind of
studied Cam even more since uh you're in
building and he's your coach, what have
you seen from him from last year
and your interaction in this off season
that makes you believe in him even more?
Cam Ward? Right. Uh you know, we have we
haven't seen him throw the ball yet. Uh
we have, but uh not in a uh live
situation, but uh
look, I I I've said it before. Like I I
just think it's really cool. I I try to
observe people from afar. Uh Cam's there
every day.
Uh obviously we can't talk ball with
him, but I can watch him interact with
the with the uh people in the building
and I I just think it's uh it's very
impressive for a a young man to walk
through the building, know everybody by
name from from the from the janitors to
the QCs to the chefs to the trainers and
addresses them by name and is such a I
mean, he's he's a a really really really
good man and uh
um
I just think his head's on the right
way. He's got the right work ethic. I I
just don't see him failing. How do you
like him and his
his personality and Brian? How will they
How will they
>> It's going to be awesome. I'm sure
they'll bicker at each other once in a
while and they'll they'll challenge each
other
challenge each other often,
um but that's the exact temperament you
want out of your quarterback. Is there a
silly element of the CBA that
you and he and Brian and he are in such
close proximity of each other and are
limited to
maybe talking about the movie you saw
and Um
yeah, I'm I'm the
even I don't even know if we can do
that, but uh you know, I I I do I would
challenge that. Obviously I'm a coach.
If a player wants to come in and get
better and you don't, that's your fault,
but you know, they they're always going
to do it where
I I'm going to stay away from that.
That's that's off my pay grade, but I
think they should be there. But what do
you make of his development? How
critical is it to make sure that running
back room where it needs to be to help
this young quarterback? Say it again. As
you look at Cam Ward's development, how
critical is it to make sure that running
back room is right? Yeah, um
always. It's you know, your
the the best way to help a young
quarterback is through run game and
defense and and I've said it before. I I
love our running back room.
Um shoot.
Just last year's uh Tony Pollard dropped
over 100 on us in uh San Francisco, so I
think he's a a a damn good football
player.
Um it's a great one-two punch. They both
run run with physicality. They both have
versatility out of the backfield, so I'm
I'm a believer in our backfield and I
think it's a it's a group that can help
our team. And another part of it you
mentioned game changers. How do you feel
you guys went about addressing adding
game changers to help him out in his
development? Um well, you're you're
always going to look for those. Um
obviously I think John Franklin-Myers, I
think Jermaine uh Jermaine Johnson are
both game changers. Obviously it's not
on the offensive side of the ball, but
those guys will get him the ball and uh
obviously uh Jeffries is there still uh
and there's plenty of guys that we
added, but uh
but you're always going to try to
uh add game changers. Um the best way to
do it and the the most financially
responsible way to do it is through the
draft and uh and hopefully we get a get
our get an opportunity to do that
throughout the uh process. Speaking of
that,
with Cam returning to play,
for you, how do you guys kind of keep
tabs on what he's able to do and you
know, the filing
of the season? Um well, we're still
allowed updates and all that stuff.
That's that's part of the you know, just
making sure that he's progressing the
right way and uh you know, he's so he's
in there. He's he's going he's working
with the trainers. He's working with the
weight room. That all that stuff is
completely legal, but uh so we're up to
date. I'm not going to put a time table
on anything, but but he's progressing
really well. What do you make of the
first uh the edge class
especially in the range where you're
picking at the top in the first and
second round? Uh I I think there's a lot
of really good football players, you
know, especially at the top top part
where we're picking. I think there's uh
I mean, you you could argue there's
three really legit dudes uh in that uh
top five range that are all deserving
and uh there's there's definitely guys
who can come in on the edge
at edge rusher. Is Bains' arm length is
that really as much of an issue as
outside is making it as two and two,
coach?
Uh when you play with as much
physicality and violence
the man gets to the quarterback. So,
that's all that matters. While Cam is
working in the building on rehab stuff,
is he also working with his quarterback
guy on Cam's side or what's the balance
of
what he's working on? Yeah, he'll he'll
work with his quarterback guy. Um
you know, I'm I'm sure he's working at
to to the best of his his ability. There
there is a program that he has that's um
um
that we're aware of and we're working
with him on in terms of uh making sure
everything's coordinated the way it
needs to be. We're talking to the people
he's talking to basically.
Uh so, we feel comfortable with where
he's at. So, that part is he doing that
doing the rehab stuff with you? Is he
out of town with that guy or is that guy
working Um
it's a it's a mixture of both. You know,
he's going to he's going to travel. He's
going to do his thing and you know,
they're they're not 100% in the
building. They're not required to be in
the building.
Uh but I do know that where wherever Cam
is, he's working to get himself ready to
play. What are some of the mechanical
things maybe that that you asked him to
concentrate on in that
that part?
He's always going to the the mechanical
stuff
for us is always going to come with his
feet. You know, that's the one thing you
as a coach, you're really not going to
mess with his arm his arm angles, his
the way he releases the ball. You're not
going to try to fix that. The way he
throws the ball is the way he throws the
ball.
Um
from a coaching staff standpoint, it's
going to tie it's going to be about
tying everything with his Speaking of
another draft-related question for you,
I'm wondering how your your view of age
in a prospect has changed. I'm sure
there's there's goods and bads to it,
but especially in the first round, does
does old matter, you know, that you can
make an impact right away, but less
upside? No, that's that's a great
question.
Uh it depends on whether or not we feel
like he maxed himself out. You know, are
we watching someone who can get better
or are we watching somebody who's who is
at his age hit the ceiling of what he's
capable of. So, it's I think every uh
when you're looking at those older guys
every player is independent of what he's
capable of in the future. The biggest
the the age of the draft, what is the
biggest benefit of these drafts getting
older, I guess, for your team as a Um
there
you could argue that they're physically
more mature and physically uh more ready
to play, but um but there's positives
and negatives to all of it.
Um
Brian
I'm sorry. Um just his his ability to
work with you know, young quarterbacks
in college. We see what he's done with
Zach and with Josh, you know,
how much did that factor in your
decision again? Like he works well with
young guys, connects with them
schematically, but also on maybe a
certain
level where these guys can develop
really quickly. Yeah, he's uh I mean, I
I've gone against Daboll plenty.
Um
you know, he he does a really good job
making it very simple for these uh for
the quarterbacks. There's it's uh it's
there's a lot of learning early, but as
they as they get the routine and as
really any system that he's he's he
finds a way to simplify it with regards
to verbage and uh
you know, he's
he's going to be really good for Cam,
especially his demeanor and the way he
coaches.
What are your thoughts on
how much joint practice helps you and
are you hoping to maybe get some lined
up for your team? Yeah, I'm I'm a big
proponent of
joint practices. My hope is that uh I I
think we're scheduled to have one with
uh Carolina.
Um I don't know who our week one and
week three opponents are going to be. I
think it's week two. Um the schedule
hasn't come out yet, but that's what we
asked for.
Um
I don't know who our two other opponents
are, but I'll definitely ask to see if
we can get a uh joint practice with
those guys also. Your team went on the
road a long time last year. Do you think
you'll do a little bit of that this
year?
Like a combo home and
and away for joint practices?
Do you think you'll do you think you'll
go on the road for some or Oh yeah, no,
we'll uh my hope is that we we go on the
road for one. We're I think we got two
home games this year for the preseason.
So, my hope is that we host two and and
hit the road for one. Carolina home or
away?
I believe it's home home. Yeah. The
clubs are going to be voting today on a
proposal
um that you know, it's sort of an
alternative if there's no CBA with the
referees negotiated where it's going to
give more oversight to the officiating
part and
what have the conversations been like
about the proposal this week here in
Phoenix? Are you talking about the refs?
Yeah. That's off my pay grade.
And they are doing it at the memo. They
did good good work getting you guys not
to talk about that
I don't I don't I don't get paid enough
for that one. I get paid good, but not
that much.
We were talking earlier, if I heard
right, you were talking a little bit
about Cam Ward and his private
quarterback coach. Is that what you were
talking about?
Yeah. Um how do you I mean, I know you
probably in your previous stop with the
Jets, you probably dealt with this as
well here with your quarterback having
their own quarterback coach on the side
that they work with. How do you as a
head coach like
organize that communication? Do you want
to stay in touch with that coach? Yeah,
you're you're you're constantly
communicating with with uh with really
and it's anyone. It's
even even when they go work out with uh
uh you know, some of these guys go to
Exos. Some of these guys have individual
workout guys. So,
uh whether it's a quarterback guy or a
trainer at any position, we're in
constant communication with the with
those groups to let them know what we do
and what we're expecting and just kind
of help them along so they can formulate
a good plan for him.
So, really
it's not just singular to to the
quarterback, it's every single position.
Have you ever had any experience where
you're not on the same page and like
things go wrong with you particularly at
the quarterback? No, those guys are
those independent
guys are really really good at
communicating and
um
and collaborating to make sure that they
do what's best for the player. Do you
know who Cam Newton works with?
We do.
I couldn't give you his name right now,
but I know we've been in constant
communication with him.
You've
known T.J. Watt for a long time. How
have you gotten to work with him last
year as a coach?
How do you see his development along in
that area and where do you think his
trajectory is? He's going to be a
coordinator really quick. I could see
him
easily
progressing the way Demeco did. You
know, he's
he's got the same mindset.
He's got the same respect from his from
his players.
K.J. K.J.'s going to be really good.
Do you think guys with linebacker
backgrounds that that translates better
to to being when you're just kind of
like the holistic knowledge that you
need? Do you think I'm I'm biased.
We we we we know the front, we know the
back. You know, it's
we've got to. You know, you've got to
understand how the D-line plays, you've
got to understand your run fits, you've
got to understand how how to defend the
run, but you also got to be able to
defend all the all the various concepts
that teams are given and
also understand the stress of for
all of it. So, he's in a way the the the
linebacker is the quarterback of the
defense in terms of communicating with
the front and the back.
So, you just get a more of a global
understanding when you're in those those
positions. How hard did you try to take
him take him with you to the No, I I
would
that was a it was an understanding from
the beginning that he was off limits.
The program starts April the 7th, is
that right? It's coming. How how much
are you looking forward to that? Can't
wait. Can't wait. It's What's that like
for you and kind of being a head coach
for the first time and kind of being in
front of the team for the first time?
Used to it, but
you know, we're all set, we're ready to
go and
you know, like I like I tell everybody
that this gap between the end of the
season
the the first part of the end of the
season is good cuz you need to you need
to get away from everybody, but we're
bored. We miss our players. Looking
forward to seeing them. What do you hope
to accomplish?
It's really [snorts] just setting the
foundation.
It's football 101. You're at the
beginning of everything and
so, we're just trying to go step
step-by-step, introduce our schemes,
introduce what we the expectations both
of as coaches and as players and
hopefully we can roll into the training
camp feeling really good about
everything.
Could you offer a comment on Lavonte
David retiring and his impact on Oh,
man.
Special player.
Hopefully we see him in the hall one
day.
But it's been fun, you know, he's
he's been one of the best linebackers
obviously just studying linebackers
and being a fan of linebackers, he's
been one of the more impactful guys in
football for a long time.
I'm working on a story about Caleb
Williams. Curious what you think the
biggest challenge
that he presented you last year And you
just missed an unbelievable quote.
Really? Yeah, man. Somebody else came to
you first? Yeah. Oh, no. No, he's a
He
he he I thought Ben did an outstanding
job. You know, he's
I mentioned that he reminded me a little
of and I don't I'm not trying to put a
ceiling on him cuz he could be better,
but Russell Wilson where you know, like
it didn't matter how the game started,
you knew as the moment got bigger and
bigger and bigger, he was going to
become more and more dangerous and
and it and it proved in his fourth
quarter heroics. I mean, the guy just
the game is never over. I don't care
what the score is, I don't care what the
situation is.
I think the play the the throw he made
in the playoff game proves that. But
he's a special young man, special
talent. He's only going to get better.
You mentioned Ben
what's the challenge for young coach to
maintain success? It's one thing to
build it up, it's another to
I imagine that the dynamic changes when
you kind of taste it and now you've got
maybe Yeah, it's
the the challenge for for all of us
coaches is going to be in adversity. You
know, they had a really nice season last
year and
you know, I I I look at a guy like Kyle
Shanahan who it hasn't been all
peaches and cream, right? It's he's had
some some bad seasons, but he's
weathered the storm of adversity, he's
kept the organization moving in the same
direction and and Ben Ben is
a very very talented football coach.
He's one of the better ones in football
and
and there's no doubt he'll he's going to
keep that thing rolling for a while.
What was your biggest biggest takeaways
from being teammates on on watching
Brock Purdy for a year being on the same
team
I love facing him in practice. What what
did you get away from Love Brock.
He
he's he's a very special player. He's a
goddamn good football player. He really
is. Like the way he layers the ball, the
way he
the way he moves in the pocket, his
off-schedule stuff, his his his calm
demeanor.
You know, he's he's
he's he's an I don't want to say
underrated, but
he's loved in San Francisco. He's a he's
I know Kyle loves him. So, he's
deserving of everything he's got. Coach,
you were the
only minority head coach hired in this
cycle
and this comes,
you know, right before the league
changes the accelerator program to open
up to the demographic background and on
top of that they pulled funding from the
minority offensive assistant program
that started in 2022.
What do you think? Do you think the NFL
is still serious about its DEI
efforts in coaching hires? I I do, you
know, it's um
I it's my answer would be really really
long. I'm going to keep it short. I do
know that the league office is it is
very important to them. I do know that
they're working relentlessly to try to
figure out the best way to do this.
But I also know that when you look at
ownership around the league, they're
always going to do their best to hire
the best people.
I think football is one of the greatest
melting pots and examples of melting
pots and and really an example to the to
the world of what a
what an NFL locker room and a and a
coaching staff and a building looks like
with all the different mix of people,
the the demographics and the mixture of
people is
as mixed as you can possibly get in an
NFL locker room and or building for that
matter. So, I know they're relentlessly
working on trying to find a ways to make
it make it better and I think over time
they'll find the right formula.
I just wanted to ask quickly Last two
right here, guys.
The league is moving toward more and
more joint practices the last couple
years and preseason going from four to
three, maybe even going down in the
future with the 18 game
From a coaching perspective, how is that
something you want to try to do is get a
team to play practice in here in the
next summer? And the what do you think
the value is in this? Is there some more
value than the
Yeah, I'm I'm a big I'm a advocate for
joint practices.
I do I don't believe in the
two joint practices in one week. I
believe in one per team. So, I want
three of them if we could, but uh
I think they're it's a really good way
to have a
game-like experience that's controlled.
I mean, they they it is amplified and
the intensity is a lot is a lot higher.
To do it for one day, I think it's very
beneficial for the players especially
when you talk health and safety. Why not
do it for the second day?
Because that's when
That's when the coaches and the players
go into their meeting rooms and they
they they talk about how they just got
their asses kicked and then the next day
is all about fighting. So, it's a it's a
waste of waste of energy, waste of
Last one, T.D.
How do you handle a prospect that has
some background issues?
Um
Handle a prospect that has a background
like a How do you handle your evaluation
of From a character standpoint?
>> Playing that into the You know, I've
talked about it before that culture
culture is kind of cliche in the sense
that
you know, they think well, oh someone's
going to come in and they're bringing a
culture. Well, what is that culture? The
culture is whatever comes out of my
mouth.
But from a from a wording standpoint,
but ultimately culture is what you bring
into the building.
And so, the discipline of maintaining
and and bringing in people who are
capable of executing your culture. So,
from a character standpoint
it is difficult when you're looking at
this dude who's got all the measurables,
he's got all the talent in the world,
but he's a character problem.
The discipline is to walk away from that
person to maintain your culture
knowing full well that that person has a
high risk of bust. Now, as the draft
gets deeper and deeper, you'll be a
little bit more lenient with regards to
character, but
if you truly want to turn over your
culture, you've got to be really
disciplined with regards to character.
Yeah.
You've had your learning experiences. We
all have and
unfortunately you learn the hard way
especially early in the draft. I'm not
going to mention who, but I'm sure you
guys can figure it out.
Yeah.
Like I said, the the later you go in the
draft, the more lenient you'll get, but
um
but I've also learned that history has a
tendency to repeat itself.
Thank you guys. You know, I appreciate
you guys.
Okay.